All right, we pick up on צדי עמוד ב Tzadi Amud Bet
and we were talking, we are moving on now to the discussion
about whether the גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh applies only to the right
thigh or to both thighs. The Rabbis say both thighs, we rule
that way, thighs, thighs, also. Rabbi Yehuda says only one, so let's
take a look. Well, we didn't see Rabbi Yehuda in the mishna,
but we know him from before, so let's take a look. מתניתין
לא כרבי יהודה, Matnitin lo k'Rabbi Yehuda, we are now on צדי
עמוד ב, Tzadi Amud Bet, six lines down the wide lines, two
dots. Our mishna's not like Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in
the braisa, רבי יהודה אומר אינו נוהג אלא באחת, Rabbi Yehuda omer
eino noheg ela b'achat, it only applies at one of the sides,
or, you know, or one of the גיד Gid if you want
to be technical. והדעת מכרעת, v'hada'at machra'at, and the, you know, the,
the opinion weighs, or towards saying של ימין,
shel yamin, that it's the right one. איבעיא להו, Ibaia lehu, so
they asked a question.
מיפשט פשיטא ליה לרבי יהודה, Mifshat pshita lei l'Rabbi Yehuda, is it,
does Rabbi Yehuda really say that it actually is the right one
and it's obvious to him? או
דילמא, o dilma, מיפשט
פשיטא ליה לרבי יהודה, mifshat pshita lei l'Rabbi Yehuda, and what does
it
mean דעת מכרעת? da'at machra'at? דעת תורה! Da'at Torah! So there you
go, there's the source of דעת תורה. Da'at Torah. Well,
it's one of the early phrases of it, not the same idea
though. It does mean that, you know, if you look at the
Torah you'll see that it's the right one. So that's what he
means. He doesn't mean my opinion is, the Torah's opinion is. או
דילמא, O dilma, or does it mean, או ספוקי מספקא ליה, o
sfukei m'sapka lei, he's really uncertain whether it's the right or the
left, he knows it's only one. ומאי דעת, u'mai da'at, what does
he mean by the opinion or the intellect, I mean not the
intellect in any way, דעת נוטה, da'at noteh, he means the opinion
inclines, the, you know, the reasoning inclines towards that direction, but not
that there's evidence that that's correct. תא שמע, Ta shema, come in
here. העצמות והגידים והנותר ישרפו בשישה עשר. He'atzamot v'hagidim v'hanotar yisrefu b'shisha
asar. So this is now talking about the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach.
So it says the bones and the sinews and any leftover meat,
so if you have anything leftover, you have to burn it on
the sixteenth of ניסן, Nisan, you don't burn on the fifteenth because
although the fifteenth it's already נותר notar because it's supposed to be
the fourteenth at night, you don't burn קדשים kodashim on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, even קדשים kodashim that are פסול, pasul, so you wait
till the day after יום טוב. Yom Tov. And now all of
these things are things that can be eaten, bones, who eats bones?
But there's marrow inside of it. So therefore, and the marrow is
considered edible and meat, and the sinews are presumably sinews that are
edible. So all these things you burn on the sixteenth of ניסן.
Nisan. ואווינן בה, V'avinen bah, we asked about this. הני גידים מאי
עבידתייהו? Hanei gidim mai avidtaihu? What's the story with these sinews? אי
גידי בשר, Ei gidi basar, if it's sinews of meat which are
edible, ליכלינהו, leichlinhu, eat them! So why say burn them the next
day? ואי דאותר, V'ei d'otar, and if they happened to have been
leftover, היינו נותר, hainu notar, that's נותר! notar! Why bother mentioning the
גידים gidim if they're edible?
And isn't נותר notar also?
I mean, yeah, but they're the חידוש chiddush is that the marrow
is considered, there's a חידוש chiddush there that the marrow is considered
meat and edible, but if the גידים gidim are edible then what's
the חידוש? chiddush?
אלא גידי צוואר, Ela gidi tzavar, it must be talking about things
like really hard sinews that are not edible like the sinews in
the, like you know, in the neck. So and therefore, so that's
true, if that's the חידוש chiddush that we're talking about ones that
aren't edible. אי לאו בשר נינהו, Ei lav basar ninhu, so if
they're not edible, they're not meat, לישדינהו, lishdinhu, then remember we learned
yesterday that if something is not fit to be eaten, and yesterday
it was only because of a prohibition, certainly if it's not physically
fit to be eaten, then there's no מצווה mitzvah to eat it
by a קרבן, korban, and therefore it's not נותר. notar. So why
do you have to burn it? Just get rid of it, throw
it in the garbage. ואמר רב חסדא, V'amar Rav Chisda, so said
Rav Chisda, לא נצרכה אלא לגיד הנשה ואליבא דרבי יהודה. lo nitzercha
ela l'Gid Hanasheh v'aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda. The חידוש chiddush is the גיד
הנשה Gid Hanasheh according to Rabbi Yehuda, where there the reason it's
not edible is not because it can't be eaten physically but because
you're prohibited from eating it. Okay and therefore it says, so and
therefore you have to burn it. But we're still back to the
question. As we learned yesterday, if you're not allowed to eat it,
even if it's just not allowed to eat it, so there's no
מצווה mitzvah to eat of the קרבן, korban, so why do you
burn it? Just throw it out, it's not נותר. notar. So the
גמרא Gemara says right, ואליבא דרבי יהודה דאמר אינו נוהג אלא באחת,
v'aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda d'amar eino noheg ela b'achat, it only applies to
one of them. Now, אי אמרת בשלמא ספוקי מספקא ליה, ei amrat
bishlama sfukei m'sapka lei, if Rabbi Yehuda should doubt which one it
applies to, right or left, שפיר, shappir, now we understand the חידוש
chiddush of this משנה mishna because you can't eat the right or
the left גיד gid but because one of them is definitely the
גיד הנשה, Gid Hanasheh, but you can't, you have to burn it.
Why? Because the other one isn't the גיד הנשה, Gid Hanasheh, right?
It's sort of like, you know, the joke, it's like, okay, I'm
holding two coins in my hands that equal 25, I'm holding two
coins in my hands that equal 25 cents, one of them isn't
a quarter, what are they? The other one is the quarter. So
here right,
one of them is the גיד, gid, but the other one is
the גיד. gid. So therefore you can't eat either of them, right?
But you have to burn them because the one that's the גיד,
gid, if you knew which it was you wouldn't have to burn,
you'd throw it out. But since you don't know which one is
the prohibited גיד, gid, you have to wind up burning both of
them. And that proves to you that according to Rabbi Yehuda there's
a doubt which one is the גיד, gid, not that he knows
for sure because then you'd be back to square one. Don't eat
it, throw it out, why is it, why are you burning it?
Yes.
But if one of them is not the גיד, gid, the other
one is the גיד. gid. Right. Therefore you have to eat it
within the time allowed.
No, you're not allowed to, meaning, meaning if you have, if I
by eating this am maybe transgressing the prohibition of גיד הנשה, Gid
Hanasheh, then rather passively don't do the מצוה. mitzvah. Now actually you're
right, you're not just passively not doing the מצוה, mitzvah, you're also
passively transgressing לא תותירו Lo Totiru until morning. But nevertheless, better to
passively transgress than to actively transgress.
But if you have the intention of not eating something that you're
supposed to eat,
oh wait, that's פיגול, pigul, which
is that's an interesting question.
That's an interesting question. I'm not sure that the כהן Kohen is
specifically thinking at the time I'm doing it with the on the
intention. Like, if it's just a natural consequence of what's going to
happen, but he's not, I mean פיגול pigul is only if there's
a very specific intent to do it incorrectly. So he's actually, and
by the way, I should say there's a more obvious answer. פיגול
pigul is only when you intend to eat it in the wrong
time, not when you don't intend to eat it in the right
time. If you do it intent to be מותיר, motir, to leave
the meat over, it's not פיגול. pigul. Okay. But you are right
that here you're choosing between passive transgression and active transgression, and given
that you don't have a choice, so the answer is, so you'd
better transgress passively than actively. So that's the גמרא's Gemara's case. So
you see that according to רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, it's a doubt,
and therefore don't eat it but you burn it. אלא אי אמרת,
ela i amart, if you say מפשט פשיטא ליה, mifshat peshita lei,
it's obvious to him דהיתירא, deheteira, which one is permissible, דהיתירא ליכלי,
deheteira leikhlei, the one that is permissible, eat, דאיסורא לשדייה, de'issura lishadei,
and the one that's forbidden, throw out. So there's no, you won't
be burning it. But you are burning it if one of them
you're supposed to eat, but you don't know which one. אמר אביקא
בר חנינא, Amar Avika Bar Chanina, let's see the answer in our
text. אמר אביקא בר חנינא, Amar Avika Bar Chanina, לעולם אימא לך
מפשט פשיטא ליה. leolam eima lach mifshat peshita lei. No, maybe רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda does know which one is the גיד הנשה. Gid
Hanasheh. והכא במאי עסקינן, Vehacha bemai askinan, what are we talking about?
כשנתלה בספק גידין, Keshenitala besafek gidin, you originally knew which was the
right and the left one, but then somehow they got mixed up.
So therefore you could have a case where where you don't eat
it but you have to burn it, because you do know that
the right גיד gid is the גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh and the
left one is not. But you don't know which is the right,
which is the left. Obviously you knew at one time, but then
they got mixed up. And therefore you can't eat either, but you
have to and but you have to burn them because one of
them you were supposed to eat. Since you don't know which one,
you have to burn both, but you're not eating them. So therefore
we have a way of dealing of explaining this ברייתא braita about
burning the גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh of a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
or גיד, gid, but we're now saying it means a גיד הנשה,
Gid Hanasheh, and even assuming רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda knows which is
which is the forbidden one in a scenario where they got mixed
up. You had a question, Michael?
No, I thought he was specifically going to give that kind of
an answer.
But but maybe you do it.
But the other, but I do have a question because why he
says one is because גיד אחד? Gid echad? We'll find out.
We don't know yet why it says גידי הנשה. Gidei Hanasheh. We
can guess, but we can find out, so let's wait. Okay. So
צ''א ע''א, Tzadi-Aleph Amud Aleph, top of the גמרא. Gemara. רב אשי
אמר, Rav Ashi amar, Rav Ashi says, לא נצרכה אלא לשומנו. lo
nitzrecha ela leshumno. It has nothing to do with רבי יהודה's Rebbi
Yehuda's position. It has to do with the fact, although שומן, shuman,
he uses the word שומן shuman here rather than חלב, chelev, because
the fat around the גיד הנשה, Gid Hanasheh, the משנה Mishna actually,
well, it depends how you read the משנה, Mishna, but anyway,
but certainly we're going to have a discussion whether that fat around
the גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh is prohibited fat. Is it prohibited fat?
Is it prohibited גיד הנשה? Gid Hanasheh? The basic answer is it's
not prohibited. It's only biblically it's only at most a rabbinic problem.
So he says why does it say you burn the גיד gid
on the קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach?
Because we're talking about the fat that's around the גיד. gid. Once
you have and that you're not going to eat because there's at
least rabbinically restricted to eat that. But because biblically you are allowed
to eat it, so then it is נותר, notar, and therefore you
have to burn it. Right? Because you're trying to get that middle
position where on the one hand you haven't eaten it for a
reason, and on the other hand it's still נותר notar and you
burn it. So what's that middle position? If there's something you really
are not allowed to eat, you should just throw it out. So
he says the fat, the fat around the גיד. gid. דתניא, Detanya,
what?
Then you use the fat for the fire.
What? That's true too. דתניא, Detanya,
שומנו shumno מותר, mutar, the fat around the גיד gid is permissible,
וישראל קדושים נהגו בו איסור. Veyisrael kedoshim nahagu bo issur.
But because the Jewish people are holy, they've separated from the fat
around the גיד הנשה. Gid Hanasheh. And therefore since you're not going
to eat, when it says don't eat the גיד gid and burn
it, it means the fat around the גיד. gid. The גיד gid
maybe you definitely don't eat because it's a גיד הנשה Gid Hanasheh
and we either rule like the חכמים Chachamim and both are forbidden
or רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and we know which one is forbidden.
So obviously you're not eating the גיד. gid. The חידוש chiddush is
you're even burning the fat around the גיד. gid. That you didn't
eat that fat because of the practice of not to eat it,
but because biblically it's actually edible, you have to burn it, it's
נותר. notar. Now here, actually, Joel, your question is even more pressing.
Because here you're transgressing a biblical prohibition of leaving over to the
the meat, right? And only because the only thing standing between you
and doing this is a is a מנהג minhag essentially, a practice.
And we do know that sometimes, say, the rabbis are telling you
to passively transgress. Okay. And but here you're talking about just like
a מנהג minhag not to eat. And yes, that is I mean
quite astounding. Or just we would just note that now, but you
know it is true that it's very common for say the rabbis
are telling you to passively not do certain things, not do certain
מצות. mitzvot. But the fact that even observing the
מנהג... minhag...
is certainly notable. The גמרא Gemara here does not see this as
problematic; it just takes it for granted and says you're not going
to eat it and therefore you're going to burn it, but because
you're going to burn it, says biblically really there's no נותר. notar.
Okay, so let's take a look at the next answer.
The reason for this מנהג minhag is what? Not to eat the
גיד?
gid? We'll see, we'll see when we get to it. It's coming
up in the גמרא Gemara in just one, one page. Okay. רבינא
אמר לא נצרכה אלא כרבי יהודה אמר שמואל. Ravina amar lo nitzrecha
ela k'Rabbi Yehuda amar Shmuel.
Not רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, this idea about burning this גיד gid
of the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach works like רבי יהודה אמר שמואל.
Rabbi Yehuda amar Shmuel. דאמר רבי יהודה אמר שמואל, d'amar Rabbi Yehuda
amar Shmuel, similar answer to before about the fat around the גיד,
gid, שני גידים הם. shnei gidim hem. There are two of these
sinews in the thigh. פנימי סמוך לעצם אסור. pnimi samuch l'etzem asur.
Maybe look at your picture again, Joe. פנימי סמוך לעצם אסור. pnimi
samuch l'etzem asur.
The inner one—meaning if you think about the thighs of the animal
standing next to each other, this means the inner thigh where the
legs face each other. So where the גיד gid goes down on
the inner thigh, where it's near the top leg bone there, the
thigh bone, so that—is that the thigh bone? The one that goes
from your hip to your knee? Okay, so the thigh bone. So
where it's next to the thigh bone, that is biblically forbidden, וחיבין
עליו, v'chayavin alav, and you will transgress the biblical prohibition of גיד
הנשה. Gid HaNasheh. That is a real biblical גיד הנשה. Gid HaNasheh.
Basically the גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh is only in the area between
the hip and the knee because only that's considered the thigh, although
it continues further, that's not biblically prohibited. And it's only the one
on the inner part of the thigh; apparently there's a similar sinew
that goes on the outer, which is not the biblical one. We'll
maybe take a look at Joe's picture in a minute. Okay, so
that's biblical and you transgress.
סמוך לבשר, samuch l'basar, the one that is not by the thigh
bone but is by the fleshy part and it's towards the outside
of the thigh, אסור, asur, that's rabbinically prohibited, ואין חיבין עליו, v'ein
chayavin alav, and you do not transgress because it's only rabbinic. So
similar to the other answer, here biblically you're allowed to eat that
גיד. gid. So since biblically you're allowed to eat that outer one,
it is no נותר notar and it has to be burned, but
you didn't eat it because the rabbis say don't eat it. So
that is the case where in this case of קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, on the one hand, it is something that there was a
reason you didn't eat it, either because it was the fat around
the גיד gid or because it was a rabbinic גיד. gid. There's
a reason you didn't eat it, but nevertheless, since the תורה Torah
says you're still obligated to eat it and able to eat it,
it halakhically is considered נותר notar and rather than throwing it out,
you actually go ahead and burn it. Okay, so that is how
we deal with that issue. We're left with the question about how
maybe rabbinic rulings we understand tell us passively not to do certain
things, but even to the point where even a מנהג minhag does
is actually quite surprising. Yes, Charlie, let me Joe, cause I see
the picture there? Can I see that? And get closer.
Yes, this מנהג minhag overriding something, if we don't do, it's an
איסור כרת?
issur kareth? Well, no, there's an איסור כרת issur kareth for eating
נותר. notar. There's not an איסור כרת issur kareth for allowing...
No, for the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, we have to eat the
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach.
No, that's only if you didn't eat a כזית. kezayit. If you
ate your כזית kezayit of your פסח, Pesach, right. So now I
guess you could make an interesting scenario, which is let's say somebody
has not yet eaten his כזית kezayit cause somebody else ate too
much. We were all partners in a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and
you went and you ate much more than you were supposed to.
The only thing I have left is this rabbinic גיד. gid. Should
I? Passively? That's a good question. That is a very good question.
I don't know. That's taking it one step further. So anyway,
here, this is a good picture. I mean it's not obvious here
because of the dimensions, but if you see, right, this one, this
is the one that goes,
is the outer one, the outer גיד gid which is only rabbinic
which we're saying, and this is the one that's biblical. Now this
actually looks more outer than inner, but this is just a question
about, it's really here it looks like front and back. We're really
talking about towards the other leg or towards... inner means towards the
other leg.
We're talking about right and left opposed to front and back in
this picture.
Right, anyway, anyway, so but the, yeah, but this, so but this
is the גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh which is going towards the bone
and this is the rabbinic.
And what is that called, actually?
It's called גיד החיצון. Gid HaChitzon. Okay. So there you go, thank
you.
You don't have your חולין Chullin book there?
I do, I have the big one back... All right, so that's
the way we've dealt with that and it is quite interesting about
rabbinic or even מנהג minhag passively not doing biblical מצוות mitzvot or
not even not doing a מצוה, mitzvah, but even passively transgressing. Now
the גמרא Gemara goes on, we're still back to the question of
whether רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda oh for god's sake, this stupid camera
once again cannot refocus. All I did was I got up for
a second. Last time it worked was up and down and back
down. I have to stop putting on the autofocus. I don't know
how to take it off. Hold on.
Ah, there we go. Okay, ah, beautiful. Okay, figured out the trick.
All right, we're on. Look at that. Must have דאוונט. davened. So
it's still trying to figure out whether it is what do you
call it whether רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda* doubt doesn't know
which one is the גיד gid *gid* or he knows which one.
So let's take a look. תא שמע Ta shema, *Ta shema* come
and hear. This is a גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* we saw actually just
a few days ago. אכל מזה כזית kezayis ומזה כזית kezayis, *Achal
mizeh kezayit umizeh kezayit*. He ate a כזית kezayis. *kezayit* of each
of the גיד gid, *gid*s, the one on the right and the
one on the left. סופג שמונים Sofeg shmonim, *Sofeig shemonim*. You get
eighty lashes, assuming you were warned separately for each of the two
transgressions. רבי יהודה אומר *Rabbi Yehuda omer*. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says
אינו סופג אלא Ella ארבעים *eino sofeig ela arba'im*. You only get
forty. Now how is that? אי אמרת בשלמא מחשב פשיטא pshita, ליה
*Ee amart bishlama machshav peshita leih*. If he knows which one you've
transgressed for the right or the left, we're going to find out
it'll be the right, שפיר *shapir*. I understand you get lashes for
the one on the right, not lashes for the one on the
left. אלא אי אמרת מספקא ליה *Ela ee amart mesafeka leih*. If
he has a doubt.
So okay, we understand that in the end you've only done one
transgression. But how do you get any lashes? We don't know which
one you transgressed for, right? Because each one you were eating we
didn't know if that was the prohibited. So הויא לה התראת ספק
*Haveia lah hatra'at safek*. It's doubtful warning. ושמיע ליה לרבי יהודה דאמר
התראת ספק לא שמה התראה *Ushmia leih leRabbi Yehuda de'amar hatra'at safek
lo shemah hatra'ah*. That doubtful warning does not count as warning. And
since before each one if you don't know if it's the one,
even if in the end you know you've done one of them
has been transgressed, but since before each one you didn't know which,
you cannot give lashes, you cannot give warning. How do you know
that?
דתניא Detanya, *Detanya*. We taught in the ברייתא Braisa. *Braita*. הכה זה
וחזר והכה זה *Hika zeh vechazar vehika zeh*. Somebody who doesn't know
who his father is. Okay? It's either his mother's first husband or
second husband. He was born right between the two, you know, or
right during that transition period. So he doesn't know who his father
is. It's one or the other. So he hit one and then
the other. Now if you hit your father and draw blood that's
a capital crime. But he didn't know. At the end he definitely
hit his father but at each act he didn't know whether he
was doing this. הכה זה וחזר והכה זה
*Hika zeh vechazar vehika zeh*. קלל זה וחזר וקלל זה *Kilel zeh
vechazar vekilel zeh*. Or he cursed one and then he cursed the
other. הכה שניהם בבת אחת *Hika shneihem bevatz achas*. Or he hit
them both at the same moment. או שקלל שניהם בבת אחת *O
shekilel shneihem bevatz achas*. Cursed them both at the same moment. חייב
chayav, *Chayav*. In any of those cases you transgress and you would
get capital punishment. רבי יהודה אומר *Rabbi Yehuda omer*. רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* says no. בבת אחת חייב *Bevatz achas chayav*. If you did
it at the same time then you could transgress and be punished
for it because then one act we know you are transgressing. בזה
אחר זה פטור *Bezeh achar zeh patur*. Sequentially you're exempt. Why? Because
even if at the end of the day you know you've transgressed
and we know you've transgressed, we don't know in each act whether
that act was the actual transgressive act. So therefore according to רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, if you didn't know which גיד gid. *gid* is
the prohibited גיד gid *gid* and it says you know how could
we say that you get one set of lashes? You should be
exempt from lashes since before each one you didn't know if you
were transgressing.
We having a Guinness sandwich?
It could be. But then the question, yeah, but then it sort
of would force us into an earlier discussion about whether you get
two sets of lashes for doing the same act at the same
time. So therefore since we want to avoid that conclusion, we're avoiding
giving that answer. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has a better answer.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says האי תנא סבר לה כאידך תנא דרבי
יהודה *Hai tanna savar lah ke'idach tanna deRabbi Yehuda*. No, there's another
position about רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* that says that you do get
lashes even if it's doubtful and that's, you know, even if each
act were doubtful and that's how we're going by. דאמר התראת ספק
שמה התראה *De'amar hatra'at safek shemah hatra'ah*. That even if it's doubtful
it counts as long as by the end of the day you
know you've transgressed, we know you've transgressed. דתניא *Detanya*. We taught in
the ברייתא *Braita*. ולא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר *Velo sosiru mimenu ad
boker*. Back to נותר *nosar*. Do not leave from the meat over
of a קרבן *korban*, and if you do leave it over, burn
it. והנותר ממנו עד בוקר באש תשרפו *Vehanosar mimenu ad boker ba'esh
tisrofu*. So בא הכתוב ליתן עשה אחר לא תעשה *Ba hakatuv litein
asei achar lo ta'asei*. The תורה Torah *Torah* gave a positive מצוה
*mitzvah* after the negative, don't leave it over, if you leave it
over, burn it. So burning it is a positive מצוה *mitzvah*. לומר
שאין לוקין עליו *Lomar she'ein lokin alav*. That the fact that there's
a positive מצוה *mitzvah* that comes to fix the transgression tells you
that if you do transgress you don't get lashes because there's a
way to fix it, burn the leftover meat. דברי רבי יהודה *Divrei
Rabbi Yehuda*. Those are רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*'s. רבי יעקב אומר Rebi
Yaakov omer, לא מן השם הוא זה *Rabbi Yaakov omer lo min
hasheim hu zeh*. רבי יעקב Yaakov, *Rabbi Yaakov* says you don't need
that reasoning. Why? אלא משום דהוי לאו שאין בו מעשה *Ela mishum
dehavei lav she'ein bo ma'aseh*. You're only transgressing passively. So here's the
way, by the way Charlie, two reasons why even though you transgressed
earlier at the top of the דף daf *daf* for נותר *nosar*,
just because of a מנהג *minhag*, it wasn't the heaviest of the
transgressions. Number one it was passive as I mentioned and number two
anyway it has an עשה *asei* to fix it. And it's passive
וכל לאו שאין בו מעשה אין לוקין עליו *vechol lav she'ein bo
ma'aseh ein lokin alav*. You don't get lashes for anything that's passive.
Now they're giving different reasons, passive or positive מצוה *mitzvah* to fix
it, but they're not giving another reason. The other reason is that
we can't give you the right warning. We can't say don't leave
over, if you do you get lashes and I'm just okay whatever
and I've got like an hour till sunrise anyway. So you don't
know whether I am going to transgress or not. Now again as
we pointed out that's not exactly the same as התראת ספק *hatra'at
safek*. It more has to do with the idea that the התראה
*hatra'ah* has to be juxtaposed to the transgression itself. But the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* phrases it as התראת ספק *hatra'at safek* because it says
at this moment that you're warning you don't know if a transgression
will take place or not take place even, you know, even given
the immediate future events. So what we see is that since he
doesn't give that as his concern, presumably he doesn't care that it's
doubtful warning. Now again that's not necessarily true, it's an argument from
silence. It could be that he's giving a more fundamental issue. The
fact that it can be fixed or the fact that it's passive
is a more fundamental reason why it's excluded from lashes. Then the
fact that we can't give you proper warning. But nevertheless, the גמרא
Gemara sees that since that wasn't mentioned, according to this approach רב
יהודה Reb Yehuda doesn't care about the doubtful warning. So now going
back, we said that if you ate from the right גיד gid
and the left גיד, gid you get one set of lashes. How
could that be according to רב יהודה? Reb Yehuda? If he doesn't
know which one is the transgression, then we didn't give you appropriate
warning before each one. And the answer is, maybe רב יהודה Reb
Yehuda doesn't need definite warning. And since by the end of the
day you've eaten both from the right and the left, we know
you've transgressed and therefore we give you lashes. But we still can
say we're not sure whether you transgressed which one is prohibited, the
right one or the left one. Let's read a little bit more
and then I'll take the question. רבי יעקב Yaakov אומר, I guess
we read that. תא שמע,
we're going to try to prove it one more time. אכל שני
גידין משתי ירכות משתי בהמות. Achal shenei gidin mishtei yereichot mishtei behemot.
If you ate from two full גידי הנשה Gidei HaNasheh from two
different sides of two different animals. So not from the right and
the left side, but from the same side from two different animals.
סופג שמונים,
you get eighty lashes because you've done two transgressions. רב יהודה אומר
אינו סופג אלא ארבעים, Reb Yehuda omer eino sofeg ela arbaim, you
only get forty. Now, מכדי קאמר משתי ירכות, Michadi ka'amar mishtei yereichot,
this is an interesting proof. Since we had to give the scenario
of two sides משתי בהמות mishtei behemot of two different animals, meaning
why did we bother giving the scenario of two sides from two
animals? Why don't we just give the scenario of the side from
a different each... the different sides from each animal? Why do we
talk about two sides from two animals? The only reason you would
want to do that is if it matters whether you're talking about
the right and the left side. Because if it doesn't matter, you
can give the same scenario of two גידי הנשה Gidei HaNasheh from
the two sides of the same animal. Since we're bothered talking about
different animals, clearly it matters which side we're talking about. So פשיטא,
it's obvious, דתרוייהו לאיסורא לרב יהודה איצטריך, detarveihu l'issura l'Reb Yehuda itztarich,
that we're trying to make sure that they are both prohibited sides
and we're talking within רב יהודה. Reb Yehuda. Since רב יהודה Reb
Yehuda says only one, we're trying to give a scenario that רב
יהודה Reb Yehuda would admit that you are doing two transgressions. That
was the only reason to give a scenario of two different animals.
So it must be that we're talking about the same side from
two animals, and therefore even רב יהודה Reb Yehuda will admit that
they are both prohibited.
And therefore, שמע מינה, shma mina, since it has to give that
scenario, this is a quite fascinating גמרא. Gemara It's not proving it
from the ruling, as Michael points out the ruling is going to
be hard to make sense of, but it's proving it from the
scenario it needs to draw. The only opinion you would care that
it's two sides of two animals is an opinion that says that
it's only one side and that we know which side it is.
So אלא שמע מינה, ela shma mina, from this, from the drawing
of the scenario you can infer מנפשיה פשיטא ליה, minafshei pshita lei,
רב יהודה Reb Yehuda knows which side is prohibited, שמע מינה. shma
mina. So that is a good proof just from the scenario before
we get to the ruling. So now the גמרא Gemara is going
to say, okay, but what about the ruling? אי פשיטא ליה, Ei
pshita lei, but if it is obvious that you get it from
one side, which we're going to say is the right one, אמאי
סופג ארבעים? amai sofeg arbaim? Why do you only get forty lashes
if you now eaten two prohibited
גידין? gidin? ולילקי שמונים v'lilki shmonim and no more, they'll get eighty
lashes. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan,
what are we talking about? כגון דלית ביה כזית, kegon d'leit bei
kezayis, that there is not a כזית kezayis, of each of each
גיד. gid. And therefore you don't... you haven't done two prohibitions. If
there's not a כזית, kezayis why do you get any lashes? Of
course, let's take a look. דתניא, because we know that there is
another debate about how much you have to eat, having nothing to
do with right side or left side, having to do with how
much you have to eat of the גיד הנשה. Gid HaNasheh. דתניא
בברייתא: Detanya bevraisa: אכלו ואין בו כזית, achalo v'ein bo kezayis, you
eat the entire גיד Gid and there's not a כזית. kezayis. That's
to be obviously a very small animal. Okay, so you ate the
entire גיד Gid and there's no כזית, kezayis, חייב, you still transgress.
Why? This is a principle we learned this before called בריה. beriah.
If you eat an entire object, even if כזית kezayis. only gives
something quantitative significance, something could have qualitative significance without quantity. So for
example, the example I gave you before is if you eat an
ant, just says don't eat ants. So you ate an ant, it
didn't say don't eat a certain amount of ant. When we say
the quantity, it's when we're... it's when you're not talking about a
whole object, it's when you're saying like don't eat prohibited meat. But
how much? Okay, so we have to give you a quantity. But
if you actually eat the entire thing, that's the transgression. So don't
eat a גיד הנשה, Gid HaNasheh, you ate the entire גיד הנשה,
Gid HaNasheh, you transgress. That's what the רבנן Rabbanan say. So they
say you ate two entire גידי הנשה Gidei HaNasheh from two different
right sides of an animal, right? And that's why you had to
say two different animals because you're eating the entire thing, so you
can't eat two parts of the same thing. And therefore you get
two sets of lashes because they say eating the entire גיד Gid
is enough regardless of how big it is. רב יהודה אומר, Reb
Yehuda omer, רב יהודה Reb Yehuda disagrees: עד שיהיה בו כזית, ad
sheyihiyeh bo kezayis, until there is a כזית. kezayit And therefore
we wanted to give this scenario, we wanted to sort of bracket,
we wanted to get to another opinion of רב יהודה. Reb Yehuda.
We're bracketing רב יהודה's Reb Yehuda issue about right and left. Give
the scenario that you have two complete right side גידי הנשה Gidei
HaNasheh and therefore we can bracket the other debate of whether it's
right or left or both sides or whatever. Fine, now we're having
a new debate. Okay, you ate two entire גידי הנשה. Gidei HaNasheh.
The רבנן Rabbanan say two sets of lashes because we don't need
a כזית, you ate an entire גיד. Gid. And רב יהודה Reb
Yehuda says, no, no, no, I need a כזית. And therefore presumably
combined I have a כזית but independently I did not and therefore
only one set of lashes, not two sets of lashes. Good, so
now we have proven that Rabbi Judah knows that it is one
side of the animal not both sides or sides. And now we're
going to figure out which one it is. So let's take a
look. And why he says only one side. So let's take a
look.
ותימא מאי, V'Teima Mai, what is the reasoning that Rabbi Judah says
only one side? אמר רבה אמר קרא הירך. Amar Rabbah Amar Kra
HaYarech. So it says אשר על כף הירך, Asher Al Kaf HaYarech,
that is on the side of the thigh. So the side, not
צד ירך, Tzad Yarech, the side, a thigh, but the side means
one particular one and which one is it? So we always assume
that we give weight to the right.
המיומנת שבירך, Hamiumenet ShebaYarech, the right one of the side, but מיומנת
miumenet does not just mean the right side, it means sort of
like the the more important side so it's the one on the
right. So that's how it goes, it use the ה, hei, the,
meaning one particular singular one. ורבנן, V'Rabbanan, why did the Rabbis say
how did they deal with the fact that it says הירך? HaYarech?
ההוא דפשיט איסורא בכולה ירך. Hahu DePashit Issura BeChula Yarech. So that
is to tell you which גיד Gid it is, the one that
goes throughout the entire thigh. לאפוקי חיצון דלא L'Apukei Chitzon DeLo to
exclude the outer גיד Gid that does not, if you remember the
picture, the outer גיד only went half down the thigh. The other
one went the entire length of the thigh, it even went further,
it even went down the entire leg. So the reason it says
the thigh is not to tell you only one side but it's
to tell you the גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh that travels the length
of the thigh and to tell you which one of those two
is the גיד.
לאפוקי חיצון דלא L'Apukei Chitzon DeLo to exclude the outer one that
does not go the entire length. ורבי יהושע בן לוי אמר, V'Rabbi
Yehoshua Ben Levi Amar, so that's one explanation from הירך, HaYarech, the,
that we learn it's only the one on the right. Rabbi Yehoshua
Ben Levi says אמר קרא Amar Kra the verse says בהאבקו עמו,
BeHe’avko Imo, that this is his side his whatever the גיד was
moved in his sort of fighting with or wrestling with the angel.
So כאדם שחובק את חבירו KeAdam SheChovek Et Chavero וידו
מגעת לכף ימינו של חבירו. VeYado Magaat LeChaf Yemino Shel Chavero. So
it's interesting, we're going to figure it out just based on the
narrative. So the narrative is that they're struggling, בהאבקו BeHe’avko will say
it's like a moment when the dust is rising, אבק, avak, but
it could also mean like to grapple from the word like חבק
chavak which seems to be the חובק chovek here, בהאבקו חובק. BeHe’avko
Chovek. Okay, so if you're grappling and you're wrestling with somebody so
the way Rashi puts it puts it you're on the right so
the person's left is facing you, you're reaching your arm around the
person, so if you're reaching your arm around the back of the
person and you're wrestling so your right arm is going to reach
the person's right side because it's going around and grappling right if
you see think of the classic wrestling pose.
So it's actually the the outer one because you're not it's hard.
Well maybe you moved the leg from the outside but it caused
the side the גיד to move.
With your right hand?
It's well we're always assuming right-handedness, yes, there is that bias.
So I'm talking from a person who not only lefties but whose
wife and and all of my children are left-handed. So all right,
so anyway. Lucky
I'm only one left-handed person. Okay. רבי ישמעאל בר נחמני אמר, Rabbi
Ishmael Bar Nachmani Amar, so that's quite interesting that we're
learning it out from the narrative.
רבי ישמעאל בר נחמני אמר Rabbi Ishmael Bar Nachmani Amar כעובד
כוכבים נדמה לו.
KeOved
Kochavim Nidmeh Lo.
Now we're trying to figure out how he got to be on
the right of the on the right like whatever how he had
access to the right and not the left. So he says oh
the angel originally appeared to him like a non-Jew maybe the idea
that he represents עשו. Esav. דאמר מר DeAmar Mar and we know
that there's a ruling that of course Jacob was keeping that we
say ישראל שנתלווה לו עובד כוכבים בדרך, Yisrael SheNitlavah Lo Oved Kochavim
BaDerech, if you happen to be walking with a non-Jew on the
way טופלו לימינו, Toflo LeYamino, make sure he's going on your right
side. Why? Because the this is in the whole גמרא עבודה זרה
Gemara Avodah Zarah there's constantly concern about the non-Jews wanting to do
violence against the Jews speaking specifically Jews under Roman occupation. And
therefore somebody is if assuming right-handedness so if he's on your right
and you're on his left and therefore he can't like grab a
sword and stab you there with the left his left hand. So
you stay protected by keeping him on your right. So therefore since
he was on Jacob's right
therefore the angel had access to Jacob's right side. Okay. So which
is again quite fascinating because it says they were fighting the whole
night and it only happened at the end of the fight. So
the positions they were in at the beginning is a little hard
to understand. Like if he maybe did a sneak move right at
the beginning, okay, you understand, but this is something that happened like
at the end of the fight. What did you want to say
Robbie?
And it also is a very clever way of protecting your heart.
Oh that's interesting. Is the heart really more exposed because the heart
is really in the center right but it's more exposed? A little
to the left.
To the left.
Is it? Okay.
Well I would have also thought that if somebody's attacking you if
you're keeping him to the right that means you're able to access
your sword and go like that.
Yeah that's also true if you're right-handed your sword is on your
left but that's also true. if you're against the person's sword, he
can't get to it without letting you know, without right, without right,
exactly. Okay, so that's why how we know, of course how we
know that he appeared like a non-Jew? Or we don't know that.
רב שמואל בר אחא *Rav Shmuel bar Acha* קמיה דרב פפא *kamei
deRav Papa* משמיה דרבא בר עולא אמר amar *mishmei deRava bar Ulla
amar* so we have another approach which more emphasizes the מלאך malach.
*malach* aspect of the מלאך *malach* rather than the עשו Esav. *Esav*
aspect of the מלאך *malach*. כתלמיד חכם נדמה לו *ketalmid chacham nidmeh
lo* he appeared like a Torah sage. דאמר מר *de'amar mar* and
we've taught המהלך לימין רבו *ha'mahalekh liyamin rabbo* if you're walking, you
and your rabbi are walking together on the road, so if you're
going to the right of your rabbi because the one on the
right is implicitly the more important one, so הרי זה בור *harei
zeh bur* you're an ignoramus. So therefore since יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* saw
that he was, you know, this amazing visage of a מלאך *malach*
and he had the sense of this very holy person, so he
felt that he was going to walk with him on, he'll be
on the angel's left to show that the angel is more important,
that's on the right. So again, he's on the angel's left, so
the angel has access to his right thigh. Again, this doesn't really
this explains how they might have originally been situated but not how
they ended, you know, they ended the fight there. All right, anyway
that's another explanation for the right.
לרבנן *le'rabbanan* and the rabbis say מאיחורי אתא ונשייה *me'achorei ata ve'nashyei*
that he got he came from behind and he moved you know
and he sort of attacked him from behind and moved the גיד
*gid* from behind so he moved maybe both of the גיד הנשה
Gid HaNasheh *gid ha'nasheh*. Again, it's very funny because it speaks to
their initial encounter and not to the sort of ongoing fight. ונשייה
בתרוויהו *ve'nashyei betarvaihu* and he caused both of the sides to move,
which is why both are prohibited.
Right, they're, yeah, that's explaining why the rabbis say that it's not
only the right. So again, what's really interesting here is that there's
this whole debate other than the first wing which is a classic
rabbinic move of הירך *ha'yarech* which is the verse of the prohibition
and the technical terms of the verse. Here it's really tying it
into the narrative. Let's figure out the narrative. If it was the
right side גיד *gid* that moved, the right one is prohibited. If
it's both that moved, both are prohibited. And even there, how we
figure out the narrative is just total speculation, right? About normal way
people fight. He looked like this, he looked like that, he came
from the back. So it's quite fascinating that this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is seeing that as the basis for this
הלכה *halacha* question. Exactly. ורבנן האי בהאבקו עמו מאי דרשי ביה *verabbanan
hai behe'avko immo mai darshi beih* they go back to the idea
that it means grabbing in the normal way you grab and coming
around you know toward the right. So what do they do with
that verse? Again not like the verse was so clear that it
meant one or the other. Anyway, מבעי ליה לכדרבי יהושע בן לוי
*mibaei leh lekhiderabbi Yehoshua ben Levi* the other teacher Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi. דאמר רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua בן לוי *de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi* מלמד שעלו אבק *melamed she'alu avak* not the word grappling but
the word אבק *avak* of dust, that they caused dust to rise
מרגלותם עד כסא הכבוד *margelotam ad kisei ha'kavod* that the dust of
their of their grappling, the dust from under their feet as you
know you're you're wrestling, went all the way up to the heavenly
heavenly chair. כתיב Kesiv, הכא בהאבקו עמו *ketiv hacha behe'avko immo* with
the grappling or the dust raising with him, וכתיב התם *ukhetiv hatam*
it says there וענן אבק רגליו *ve'anan avak raglav* and the cloud
is the dust of his feet referring to God and God on
the heavenly chair. So it's sort of a sign of the throne
of the divine throne. What's the significance of it? I don't know
other than to say that you know obviously for חז"ל *Chazal* יעקב
Yaakov? *Yaakov* and עשו *Esav* classically represent the struggle between you know
Judaism and Rome, later Judaism and Christianity and so on, this like
immortal fight right all the way back to the original prophecy, לאום
מלאום יאמץ *leom mileom yeematz* constantly grappling with one another. So maybe
you know that's what it sort of signifies, that this constant grappling
and striving you know it reached all the way up to the
heavenly chair like it's it's to signify that sense of it's the
sort of perennial religious battle.
Okay.
Or just that they were fighting really hard.
All right, so anyway okay. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי *Amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi* למה נקרא שמו גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh, *lama nikra
shemo gid ha'nasheh*? Why was it called the גיד הנשה Gid HaNasheh.
*gid ha'nasheh*?
What does the נשה *nasheh* mean? This is just a straight you
know interpretation of the word. שנשה ממקומו *shenasha mimmekomo* that it moved
from its original location. דעלה *de'ala* and it moved you know it
went up in a different place in the body. וכן הוא אומר
*vekhen hu omer* נשתה גבורתם היו לנשים *nashta gevuratam hayu lenashim* their
their courage or their power has been removed, they became like women.
So you see there exactly so you see there thank you for
that cough Bobby. So anyway you see the word נשה *nasha* means
to move or remove. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא *Amar Rabbi Yosi
berabbi Chanina* מאי דכתיב mai de-chtiv, *mai dekhtiv* what is meant by
the verse דבר שלח אדני ביעקב *davar shalach Adonai beYaakov* or אדשם
*Adoshem* so a matter God has sent among Jacob ונפל בישראל *venafal
beYisrael* and fell among the Jewish people. דבר שלח ביעקב *davar shalach
beYaakov* a matter was sent forth through Jacob, זה גיד הנשה Gid
HaNasheh in front of you. *zeh gid ha'nasheh* that's the gid hanasheh
because that is the only sort of practice or prohibition that we
have inherited through Jacob aside from דאוונינג מעריב *davening Maariv* based on
another גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. ונפל בישראל *venafal beYisrael* and it fell among
the Jewish people, שפשט איסורו בכל ישראל Yisrael *shepashat issuro bekhol Yisrael*
it started with. of Yaakov, but now that it is a practice
that has spread throughout the entire Jewish people. Okay, so that's not
obviously it doesn't really say too much we didn't know, but it
ties in the idea of גיד הנשה to that verse. ואמר רב
יוסף ברבי חנינא, V'amar Rav Yosef berabi Chanina, מאי דכתיב, dechsiv, what
is meant by the verse ביוסף, be-Yosef, וטבוח טבח והכן, u-tevo'ach tevach
ve-hachen, slaughter a meat and prepare it, right when Joseph by the
brothers, he tells the person working over his household, prepare this meat
and present it to my brothers.
פרע להן בית השחיטה, Para lahen beit ha-shechita, first expose for them
the place where the slaughtering is done, so they can inspect it
and see that we did a good שחיטה. shechita. והכן Ve-hachen and
prepare the meat, טול גיד הנשה בפניהם, tol Gid HaNasheh bifneichem, remove
the גיד הנשה in their presence. Why in their presence? Because we
learned at the first משנה Mishna that you can't trust the butcher
to remove the גיד הנשה, so have them see that you're removing
it. כמאן דאמר Ke-man de-amar and this is with the opinion that
גיד הנשה נאסר לבני נח, Gid HaNasheh ne'esar le-vnei Noach, that not
that even בני נח, Bnei Noach, not meaning all of בני נח,
Bnei Noach, but the sons of Jacob, the prohibition right when it
says actually you could say, you know, in the first says על
כן לא יאכלו בני ישראל. Al ken lo yochlu Bnei Yisrael. How
do you explain the word ישראל in that verse? יעקב, Yaakov the
son of the son of Jacob, or בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, the
Jewish people. So that is the debate later whether it actually was
the sons of Jacob kept the prohibition of גיד הנשה. That's what
it means by בני נח. Bnei Noach. It doesn't mean all non-Jews,
it means the sons of Jacob before they became the Jewish people.
So assuming they did, now it's a דרש drash on the פסוק
pasuk where Joseph has the brothers over before he reveals himself, but
he wants to tell them: Hey guys, I know you keep kosher,
don't worry, you can inspect it, you can come into our kitchen,
you know, ask any questions you want. So therefore we're going to
שחט shecht it in front of you or show you that it
was שחט, shechted, remove the גיד הנשה. So of course, you know,
the מהרש"א Maharsha asks, how does it help that somebody else שחט
shechted it? We learned in the beginning שחיטת נכרי shechitat nochri is
not good. Well, maybe if everybody in the world is non-Jews, including
the people that are eating from it, maybe it's not so bad
if it's שחט shechted by non-Jews. He doesn't say that. He actually
says that פרע בית השחיטה para beit ha-shechita means expose for them
the place of שחיטה shechita and let them do the שחיטה. shechita.
But anyway, somehow I think that if everybody is non-Jewish, including the
people eating it, it doesn't really matter if a non-Jew does the
שחיטה. shechita.
Yeah, this is an amazing, I don't know who's talking, but this
is an amazing picture. Can you just picture Joseph talking with the
brothers, this whole
thing, you know,
occurring in front of them? It's just extraordinary.
Yeah, it's unbelievable.
Okay, yeah.
I wanted to ask a question. Didn't we also say that the
only time that something is really prohibited is if it's mentioned again
after מתן תורה? Matan Torah?
Yeah, we're going to get there. That will be exactly coming up
in this discussion, but we haven't got there. We've always been referring
to this issue, we haven't gotten to it yet. Bobby, did you
leave me? Because we didn't respond to your comment.
Enough of that, he said. Enough of that and I promise.
All right.
Anyway, okay. Okay. כמאן דאמר Ke-man de-amar if I did that. ויותר
יעקב לבדו. Vayivater Yaakov levado.
Now we're going to spend the rest of the דף with some
אגדתא agadata around Jacob. So ויותר יעקב לבדו, Vayivater Yaakov levado, Jacob
was left alone and he fought with this person, which showed that
to be an angel. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, שנשתייר על
פכים קטנים. she-nishtayer al pachim ketanim. Famous אגדתא. agadata.
Why was he left alone? Why wasn't he with his family? Oh,
he got he went back because he had to pick up some
of those little vessels that had been left behind. They moved over
everything, it says ויעבר כל אשר לו. vaya'aver kol asher lo.
So what's keeping him back? Oh, he remembered he left like a
couple of tiny, tiny little pottery vessels. מכאן לצדיקים שחביב עליהם ממונם
יותר מגופם. Mikan le-tzaddikim she-chaviv aleihem mamonam yoter mi-gufam.
From here you see that the righteous people, their property is even
more dear than their body, that they're willing to like, you know,
be alone and risk a certain amount of danger to go back
for some tiny little, you know, few bucks. וכל כך למה? Ve-chol
kach lama? Why is this? בשל שאין פושטים ידיהם בגזל. Beshel she-ein
poshtim yedeihem be-gezel. They are so scrupulous, right, because they because they
and it makes sense, right, if you know, people that don't treat
their own money with respect won't treat other people's property with respect
either. You treat other people's property with respect, it doesn't just mean
you don't want to, you know, since you don't steal so every
dollar matters because you might not have enough money. I mean that's
one way of reading it, but I think the more important way
of reading it is is that because you are so careful with
what, you know, what it means that people own property and you
respect property, you also respect your own property and it's not something
you know either.
What? Like oh, that's what you mean, you don't want somebody to
steal your stuff? I don't think so. Oh, פושטים ידיהם poshtim yedeihem
means they don't transgress גזל. gezel. I see. Because you could also
have just said yeah, מפקיר mafkir it, I leave it behind, right?
But you know, but I mean you see that people's mentality, right?
People that basically say oh who cares whatever. I'm not saying it
means that you should go crazy over little things, but but whatever.
Anyway, you do see that sometimes that people who are very careful
and respectful about, you know, the way they treat their own property
are also very respectful about the way they treat other people's property.
It's interesting that we belittle people, you know, ובכל מאודך, u-bechol me'odecha,
right? Because it says יש אדם שחביב עליו ממונו יותר מגופו. yesh
adam she-chaviv alav mamono yoter mi-gufo. We tend to think like Rashi's
saying ah
that's like, you know,
sort of like a guy who's not so good, he's
like oh right his money. But according to this, it'd be a
pure צדיק. tzaddik. Yeah, I mean it can't mean it
literally, right? I mean, but you know, the way you say this,
why is it bother schlepping back, is it your time more valuable?
You're right, it can't literally mean that he would... Give up his
life over a few dollars, but it does it's a little bit
of an exaggeration. But you're right, it means that he's willing to
leave himself alone and go שלעפּ shlep back or whatever just for
some small little thing. Okay, ויאבק איש עמו עד עלות השחר, Vayeavek
ish imo ad alot hashachar,
and a person struggled with him until the morning. אמר רבי אבא
בר כהנא, Amar Rabbi Abba bar Kahana, מטעם תלמיד חכם שלא יצא
יחידי בלילה. mita’an d’talmid chacham shelo yeitzei yachidi balaila. This also ties
into the previous point about, you know, he was risking himself by
going back at night, but here we see that a תורה Torah
sage should not go out alone at night. Why do you know?
Because since he was alone, which it shouldn't be anybody, so תוספות
Tosafot talks about how maybe, you know, there's a there's also concern
about מזיקים mazikim and not just people, so maybe the מזיקים mazikim
particularly attack the תורה Torah sages. But you're right, it's not exactly
clear why it's just a תורה Torah. sage. Anyway, but you see
that things are a little bit more dangerous at night, right? And
that when it became daybreak the angel was ready to leave. So
night is a more dangerous time, especially for supernatural forces. So therefore,
don't be don't be alone at night. And that ties into the
fact that יעקב Yaakov was a little bit willing to risk that
because he was going back even for these tiny things. רבי אבא
בר כהנא אמר מהכא. Rabbi Abba bar Kahana amar meihacha. He says
from here, הנה הוא זרה את גרן השערים הלילה, Hinei hu zoreh
et goren hase’orim halaila, right that by what's his name, by בועז
Boaz he's going to be threshing the granary that night, so why
did נעמי Naomi know that why did רות Ruth why did נעמי
Naomi know that that he was staying? Maybe he was going to
go home afterwards? No, because once he's stuck there at night he's
going to stay there there. He's not going to go home alone.
Still doesn't really explain it, you'd think that בועז Boaz who owns
all these fields would have somebody that he could have to walk
back with him. Anyway, רבי אבהו אמר מהכא Rabbi Abbahu amar meihacha
from here, וישכם אברהם בבקר, Vayashkem Avraham baboker, this is just proving
that you're not supposed to be alone at night.
Or what was he doing alone then?
Well, that's why he didn't go home, he stayed inside of the
granary.
But he's alone there too.
Yeah, but that's not as bad as יצא יחידי, yeitzei yachidi, being
out on the street. וישכם אברהם בבקר, Vayashkem Avraham baboker, אברהם Avraham
woke up early in the morning. Now our י"ס YS and ויחבש
Vayachavosh says it's talking about the עקידה. Akeidah. So, but of course
the problem is that he took two people with him. So תוספות
Tosafot has the end of the verse is אל המקום אשר עמד
שם, el hamakom asher amad sham, it's where he was just standing
to argue with with God about סדום ועמורה. Sodom and Amorah. That's
וישכם. Vayashkem. And there he was alone, it doesn't mention anybody else
was there. So why did he wait till the morning? Because he
didn't want to go out alone at night. ורבנן אמרי מהכא, Verabbanan
amri meihacha, from here, לך נא ראה את שלום אחיך ואת שלום
הצאן, Lech na re’eh et shalom achecha ve’et shalom hatzon,
when בנימין Binyamin is sent
excuse me יוסף Yosef is sent by
יעקב Yaakov go check how your brothers are doing. So it says
ראה, re’eh, go see how they're doing which usually means that it's
during the daytime. ורבא אמר מהכא, Verava amar meihacha, ויזרח לו השמש
כאשר עבר את פנואל, Vayizrach lo hashemesh ka’asher avar et Pnuel,
which is funny because that's really the same point of the verse
before that after the fight it says then the sun rose up
so you see that he was fighting during the night. That's very
strange why it needed that פסוק pasuk that was much clearer from
the earlier verse. Okay now moving on. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi
Akiva, שאלתי את רבן גמליאל ואת רבי יהושע באיטליז של אמאום, sha’alti
et Rabban Gamliel ve’et Rabbi Yehoshua be’italiz shel Imaum, I asked רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and רבי יהושע in the in the butcher market
of this place called אמאום, Imaum, שהלכו ליקח בהמה למשתה בנו של
רבן גמליאל, shehalchu likach behema limishtei beno shel Rabban Gamliel,
they were going and buying a cow or whatever major side of
beef for this big you know wedding feast of the son of
רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. כתיב, so here's what I asked him. You
know what do you do if you're a couple of Rabbis and
you're around doing your shopping, you talk תורה. Torah So I said
to them, it says ויזרח לו השמש, Vayizrach lo hashemesh, that the
sun shone forth. וכי שמש לו לבדו זרחה? Vechi shemesh lo levado
zarcha? It shone for him. What, the sun is only shining for
יעקב? Yaakov It shines for the whole world. What's the point of
for him? הלא לכל העולם זרחה, Halo l’chol ha’olam zarcha, the sun
shines for the whole world shines for the whole world. אמר רבי
יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, so said רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, which is
interesting because he wasn't part of this little party here, so maybe
he was I don't know one of the minor Rabbis that was
around there. It's funny where רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak comes from. שמש
הבאה בעבורו זרחה בעבורו. Shemesh haba’a ba’avuro zarcha ba’avuro.
The sun that set early for him in a different narrative, here
rose early for him. Since we've been talking about how you know
it's dangerous being alone at night and the whole fight only ended
because it was sunrise. So therefore what we're saying is God caused
the sun to rise early to like you know end the fight
early. Okay, so therefore why and why did the sun rise early
for him? Because at another time it had set early for him.
Had to make up the lost time. So דכתיב, where do where
did it set early for him? One verse says ויצא יעקב מבאר
שבע וילך חרנה, Vayeitzei Yaakov miBeer Sheva vayelech Charana, he went from
באר שבע Beer Sheva to חרן Charan when he was running away
from עשו. דכתיב ויפגע במקום, dechsiv vayifga bamakom,
he encountered the place and he slept there. So what does it
mean he encountered, sounds like he bumped into it, he wasn't expecting
to hit into the place. How do you what does that mean?
So כי מטי לחרן, kimatei l’Charan, when he came to חרן. Charan.
So first it says ויצא יעקב מבאר שבע וילך חרנה, Vayeitzei Yaakov
miBeer Sheva vayelech Charana, it sounds like he'd already arrived in חרן.
Charan. And then it says, oh he encountered this place which was
בית אל Beit El and he you know had his dream. How
would he be in בית אל Beit El if he'd already arrived
in חרן? Charan? So the פשט pshat says to the verse is
he was going to חרן Charan and before he reached there he
slept over in this in בית אל. Beit El. But here we're
saying no, no, no, he got to חרן. Charan. When he got
to חרן, Charan, אמר he said, אפשר עברתי על מקום שהתפללו אבותי
ואני לא. efshar avarti al makom shehitpalelu avotai va’ani lo. Is it
possible I passed by the place that my forefathers had prayed and
I did not sort of respect that place and pray there? So
which was means בית אל. Beit El. Now the problem here is
I should say that we never sort of see such an important
real in בית אל. Beit El.
We do see by אברהם Avraham that when he comes into the
land of כנען, Kna'an, it says בית אל מים והעי
מקדם, Beit El mi-yam veha-Ai mi-kedem, but that he's not in בית
אל, Beit El, בית אל Beit El is westward. So what does
it mean, "Oh, this place my forefathers prayed"? And we also know
what is בית אל? Beit El? בית אל, Beit El, לוז, Luz,
whatever, it's got this whole thing about the ladder. So in the
rabbis basically conflate the place that יעקב Yaakov had this dream, which
is בית אל Beit El לוז, Luz, with ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? שער
השמים Sha'ar HaShamayim is got to be הר הבית Har Habayit in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So they basically assume that's what we're talking about. Oh,
we'll discuss in a minute how it fits in with בית אל
Beit El לוז Luz naming. So if that's what we're talking about
of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, oh, well we know, you know, אברהם Avraham with
the whole עקידה Akeidah which we're about to read, right, that was
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. We assume they attribute it to יצחק Yitzchak when it
says ויצא יצחק לשוח בשדה. Vayetze Yitzchak lasu'ach basadeh. Once אברהם Avraham
is there, so יצחק Yitzchak is there and יעקב Yaakov is there
and we're all talking about הר הבית Har Habayit in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
That's what we're talking about. So he says: How could I have
passed over such an important place? I was in a big rush
to get to חרן, Charan, but you know even when you're in
a big rush you gotta show respect to those places and maybe
also, you know, I need God's help, which is an interesting thing,
right, that God sort of, you know, which is pretty much true
with all of the fathers until you sort of, you know, which
is sort of God is initiating much more the conversation and then,
you know, than they are. But it is interesting that here יעקב
Yaakov is running away and he's not turning to God. He only
has the conversation with God when God initiates the conversation. So anyway,
so how could it be, so here we're having יעקב at least
being somewhat of the initiator after having skipped over it. How could
it be that I passed over and I did not pray there?
קיהב דעתיה למיהדר, Ka-yahev da'ateih lemihadar, so he thought that he was
going to, so he said: Oh, I gotta turn around and go
back. קפצה ליה ארעא. Kafetzah lei are'a. So the land jumped up
to meet him. Okay, קפיצת הדרך, kefitzat haderech, you might have heard
that phrase.
מיד ויפגע במקום. Miyad Vayifga bamakom. He encountered the place. So that's
what it means to encounter, right? He wasn't expecting it, he turned
around and next thing he knew, two minutes later, he was all
the way back at הר הבית Har Habayit in ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. Okay, and that also, the other word of פגע paga means
to pray because now he's going to pray there. So it's a
play on the word פגע. paga. He encountered and he prayed at
that place. He jumped back to
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. כדצלי, Kadtzali, after he finished praying, בעי למיהדר, ba'ei lemihadar,
he says: Okay, now I've been, now I need to get back
to חרן. Charan. אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu, so
God said: צדיק זה בא לבית מלוני, Tzadik zeh ba leveit meloni,
this righteous person came to my inn, my place of sleeping, ויפטר
בלא לינה, veyiptar belo linah, he's going to leave without sleeping over?
Once you're here, stay a little
bit. Okay, מיד, miyad, so immediately, בא השמש. ba hashemesh. So it
says כי בא השמש. ki ba hashemesh. It sounds like the sun
set also unexpectedly. He slept there because, it doesn't say the sun
set and then he slept there. He slept because the sun set.
Made it sound like the sun set without it having been expected.
So God is manipulating the whole thing to get him to come
back and then to get him to stay. Sometimes people have to
be nudged a little to do the right thing. And now the
sun set early, so it's got to make up for lost time.
So how does it make up for the lost time? It rises
early the next day on his way back when he fights with
the מלאך. So there's a nice parallel in terms of setting early
and rising early, yeah.
No, but according to this then, if יצחק Yitzchak was מנחה Mincha
and יעקב דאוונד davened before the sun was set at all, right,
he דאוונד davened again, how do you know about it?
Good question. Maybe this isn't the תפילה. t'filla. Which is the one
that we know he דאוונד davened ערבית? Arvit? יצחק Yitzchak מנחה... Mincha...
right,
and it's פסוק pasuk like רבי יהודה. Which is the פסוק pasuk
that they quote for how do we know that he דאוונד davened
it at night?
Was it this? I thought it's...
is it this? Is it כי בא השמש? ki ba hashemesh? All
right.
And then there's, yeah, it's like the reverse of the story where
it says he didn't realize he was in this place.
Well that's what he says, he actually says, like that is a
good point too, which it says where with the פסוק pasuk אין
זה כי אם בית אלהים
ein zeh
ki im
beit elohim right, מה נורא המקום הזה mah nora hamakom hazeh אין
זה כי אם... ein zeh ki im... what was it? ויירא ויאמר...
vayeira vayomar... ואנכי לא ידעתי, ve'anochi lo yadati, right, what's the whole
פסוק? pasuk? מה נורא המקום הזה אין זה כי אם בית אלהים
וזה שער השמים.
Mah nora hamakom hazeh
ein
zeh ki im beit elohim vezeh
sha'ar hashamayim.
No, but that... ואנכי ידעתי אין זה, ve'anochi yadati ein zeh, אין
זה כי אם בית אלהים וזה שער השמים. ein zeh ki im
beit elohim vezeh sha'ar hashamayim. ויירא יעקב מאד ויצר לו. Vayeira Yaakov
me'od vayetzer lo. No, that... anyway, I can't remember. Anyway, yeah, but
it is a good question. It says I didn't know. I didn't
realize it was שער השמים. Sha'ar HaShamayim. Right. No, it doesn't say
he prayed. The תורה Torah. never says he prayed. He realized it
was שער השמים Sha'ar HaShamayim when he woke up. The idea that
he prayed is all in the מדרש, Midrash, it's not in the
תורה. But you have to say according to that, that you're right,
that he knew that אברהם Avraham and יצחק Yitzchak prayed there and
he says he calls it a מקום שהתפללו, makom shehitpalelu, that they
prayed, but he didn't realize it was like שער השמים, Sha'ar HaShamayim,
that it was the opening to the heaven. Okay. Now by the
way, how do we solve the problem that it's this is in
בית אל Beit El לוז Luz and it's not in הר הבית?
Har Habayit? So basically this is what some try to sort of
reconcile it exactly. through this מדרש *Midrash* that they basically say that
he turned around from חרן *Charan* he didn't bump into it right
away. He reached all the way to לוז Luz, *Luz* or בית
אל *Beit El* and then that's when הר הבית Har HaBayis *Har
HaBayis* came to greet him, that was his קפיצת הדרך *Kefitzas HaDerech*.
So the fact is that's how you get it happening both at
הר הבית *Har HaBayis* and at בית אל לוז *Beit El Luz*
because of this sort of folding up of geography.
All right, now what's he's supposed to be running away from עשו
*Esav*? I know.
No, but
that
shows in a way that there's a nice parallel. No, but I
should say that there's a nice parallel to the previous מדרש *Midrash*
about the פכים קטנים *Pachim Ktanim* about sort of a little bit
about a certain amount of going back and exposing yourself to danger
for the little things that matter. I mean if you want to
sort of abstract it a little bit, right? You know, oh, just
focus on the big things. No, no, no, little things matter. So
here, the little fact that it was a place that my father
had prayed and I didn't and at the time I was in
such a rush, who can worry about that, I gotta get out
of here. No, you gotta go back for the little things that
matter. So I think there's a nice parallel with the earlier point.
Okay, now we're going to have some famous מדרשים *Midrashim* about this.
מיד וישכם *Mi-yad va-yishkam* כתיב *kesiv*. Now we're going to have some
מדרשים *Midrashim* about...
Right. יש השם במקום הזה ואנכי לא ידעתי
*Yesh Hashem bamakom hazeh ve'anochi lo yadati*. Thank you. צעקה *Tze'aka*, יש
השם *yesh Hashem*... thank you very much. כתיב ויקח מאבני המקום *Kesiv
Vayikach me'avnei hamakom*, he took from the stones of the place, multiple
stones. וכתיב ויקח את האבן *Vechesiv vayikach es ha'even*, the stone under
his head. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* says obviously the פשט *pshat* is
he took one stone from the stones. But nevertheless, we're bothering that
it says the stones and then there was one stone. אמר רבי
יצחק Amar Rabbi Yitzchak *Amar Rebbe Yitzchak* מלמד שנתקבצו כל אותן אבנים
למקום אחד *melamed sheniskabtzu kol osan avanim limakom echad*, all of the
stones gathered to one place when he was trying to go to
sleep or as he was sleeping on them. וכל אחת ואחת אומרת
עלי יניח הצדיק זה ראשו *Vechol achas ve'achas omeres alai yanich hatzaddik
zeh rosho*, the righteous person will put his head on me. So
and therefore they started off as many stones, תנא וכולן נבלעו באחת
*tana vechulan nivlu be'achas*, they all got swallowed up to be one
stone because they all wanted the honor
of יעקב *Yaakov*'s head on their, on them. Okay. ויחלום *Vayachalom* he
dreamed, והנה סולם מוצב ארצה *vehinei sulam mutzav artzah*, the ladder was
on the ground. תנא כמה רחבו של סולם *Tana kamma rachavo shel
sulam*, how wide was the ladder? שמונת אלפים פרסאות *Shmonas alafin parsa'os*,
eight thousand
parsangs, which are like whatever they, I think whatever it is, like
a mile, 8,000 miles. דכתיב *Dichesiv*, how do you know? והנה מלאכי
אלוקים עולים ויורדים בו *Vehinei malachei Elokim olim veyordim bo*. The angels
are going up and down. עולים שנים *Olim shenayim*, so going up
is in the plural, so at least two angels were going up.
ויורדים שנים *Veyordim shenayim* and going down were two and assuming that
these were different angels going up than going down and that they
were going up and down in pairs, not sequentially. So therefore if
you have two going up and two coming down, when they actually
meet at one point in the ladder, it has to be wide
enough to hold four angels. Okay. וכי פגעו בהדי הדדי *Vechipgu bahadi
hadadi* when they met one another in the middle of the ladder,
הוו להו ארבעה *havu lehu arba*, there were four angels. וכתיב בי
במלאך *Vechisiv bei bimalach* and we know that one angel it says
וגוייתו *ugviyaso* his back כתרשיש *k'tarshish* was like תרשיש *Tarshish*. תרשיש *Tarshish*
was understood to be some ocean that was 2,000 פרסאות *parsa'os* wide.
So if one angel is 2,000 פרסאות *parsa'os*, so then you've got
8,000 פרסאות *parsa'os*. Okay. גמירי *Gemiri* and we know דתרשיש תרי אלפי
פרסי הוי *d'Tarshish srei alfei parsei havei* is 2,000 פרסאות *parsa'os*. Okay.
תנא עולים ומסתכלים בדיוקנו של מעלה *Tana olim umistaklin bidyukno shel ma'alah*,
they went up and down, so they went up and they saw
the image above. Now this could mean God's actual image, but רש"י
*Rashi* says it means the image that is on the heavenly throne
because of the vision has said that the heavenly throne on one
side has the face of a man, on one side a lion,
on one side an eagle. So the man in rabbinic literature is
that the man who's on the heavenly throne, the face is the
face of יעקב *Yaakov*. Okay. By the way, דיוקן *diyukan* is from
the Greek word of icon, which means image. Okay. So there was,
they looked at the image above on the heavenly throne. ויורדין ומסתכלים
בדיוקנו של מטה *Veyordin umistaklin bidyukno shel mata*. And they came back
and they looked at יעקב *Yaakov* and they said, "Hey, didn't we
see that up there?" So באו לסכנו *bo liskeinei*, they wanted to
injure יעקב *Yaakov* because they thought like, you know, he was competing
against God or they were very jealous that it was his image
that was on the heavenly throne. מיד והנה השם נצב עליו *Miyad
vehinei Hashem nitzav alav*. God right after it says they were going
up, God was standing now what's the עליו *alav*? The פשט *pshat*
of the פסוק *pasuk* usually עליו *alav* is over the ladder, right?
סולם מוצב *sulam mutzav* God is standing above the ladder and the
image of God is up above in the heaven. But here it's
reading God was standing above יעקב *Yaakov* to protect יעקב *Yaakov* because
of the angels. נצב עליו *Nitzav alav*. אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש
*Amar Rebbe Shimon ben Lakish*, אלמלא מקרא כתוב אי אפשר לאומרו *ilmalei
mikra kasuv iy efshar le'omro*. Had it not been in the verse,
you wouldn't be able to say such a thing. כאדם *Ke'adam*, what
does it mean God is standing over him? How does somebody, what
does somebody do if they're standing over a person? How would they
do to protect the person? So it says כאדם שמיף על בנו
*ke'adam shemeif al bino*, like he's taking like, you know, a piece
of cardboard or whatever, a fan and you fan over somebody. Like
imagine somebody standing over to care for somebody. So why are you
fanning? So either to protect from the heat or that's what רש"י
*Rashi* says or the מהרש"א *Maharsha* says it could even just mean
fanning to keep away the flies. So meaning the point is that's
why it's like if it were not written we couldn't say it,
that God is taking such sort of so attentive to יעקב *Yaakov*
that נצב עליו *nitzav alav*. Again, obviously imaging of God saying, "I'm
here to protect you and I'll be with you," and so on,
that He's even like fanning יעקב. Okay. הארץ אשר אתה שוכב עליה,
Ha'aretz asher atah shochev aleha, the land that you're sleeping on, I
will give to you. My רבותי, rabosai, what do you mean big
deal? You're going to give me two square feet? The land I'm
sleeping on, you're going to give to me and my children? Right,
so אמר רבי יצחק no, מלמד שקיפל הקדוש ברוך הוא כל ארץ
ישראל והניחה תחת יעקב אבינו. melamed shekipeil Hakadosh Baruch Hu kol Eretz
Yisrael venichah tachat Yaakov Avinu. He caused, and this fits in with
the whole idea of folding the geography, so not only have we
folded it and gotten הר הבית to be on לוז, but the
entire land of Israel has now been folded and put under יעקב
שתהא נוחה להיכבש לבניו shetinoach lehikaivesh levanav to show that it'll be
easy to conquer just like you can sleep on this one plot
of land, and that's the extra promise, not just I'm giving you
this land, but it'll be easy to conquer, it's all underneath you.
Okay, ויאמר שלחני Vayomer shalcheni back to the struggle with the angel,
send me free כי עלה השחר ki alah hashachar because it's sunrise.
So אמרו לו, Amru lo, so he so יעקב said to the
angel גנבא את Ganava ata you're either a robber, a burglar, או
קוביוסטוס את. o kubyustus ata. רש״י Rashi says קוביוסטוס kubyustus means a
murderer. תוספות in another גמרא says it means a card player. What
type of people are afraid of the day? You must be either
a burglar or a card player, you know, and you do your
dirty stuff at night and as soon as it's sunrise you got
to go into hiding. שמתירא מן השחר shemityarei min hashachar you're afraid
of daybreak. אמר לו Amar lo he says to him no, מלאך
אני Malach ani I'm an angel. So why do I have to
leave?
ומיום שנבראתי לא הגיע זמני לומר שירה עד עכשיו umiyom shenivresi lo
higia zemani lomar shirah ad achshav I had not had an opportunity,
it was not my turn to praise God and to sing to
God until this morning, so you got to let me go because
I got to go up to heaven to sing to God. מסייע
ליה לרב חננא Mesayeiah leh le-Rav Chanana because you can't say that
angels aren't allowed to do their to be here during the daytime,
right, because the whole angels that came you know to tell you
know to שרה Sarah and אברהם, Avraham, whatever, they're all in the
daytime. So why all of a sudden does this angel have to
leave? Huh? He has to leave because it's his turn to sing
to God. Okay. מסייע ליה לרב חננא Mesayeiah leh le-Rav Chanana to
support רב חננא Rav Chanana אמר רב, Amar Rav, דאמר רב חננא
אמר רב, d'amar Rav Chanana Amar Rav, שלוש כיתות של מלאכי השרת
אומרות שירה בכל יום. Shalosh kitos shel malachei hashareis omros shirah bechol
yom. Three groups of heavenly angels pray to God every day, presumably
it means they're constantly rotating. So since they're constantly rotating,
it was only it was a special opportunity that this angel had
to say שירה shirah today. Now, once we're talking about that, אחת
אומרת קדוש Achas omeres Kadosh one group says holy, אחת אומרת קדוש
Achas omeres Kadosh one group says holy, ואחת אומרת קדוש ה׳ צבאות
Ve-achas omeres Kadosh Hashem Tzevaos like קדוש קדוש קדוש ה׳ צבאות. Kadosh
Kadosh Kadosh Hashem Tzevaos. Also it shows that it's very portioned out
how much an angel gets to do. So that also fits with
this theme like finally I got my chance to sing to God,
that every angel only gets a little bit of an opportunity. It's
just one word? Right. ומיתיבי U'meisvei and now he has the upshot,
we have a ברייתא. חביבין ישראל לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא יותר ממלאכי
השרת. Chavivin Yisrael lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu yoser mimalachei hashareis.
Israel is dearer to God than the heavenly angels. שישראל אומרים שירה
בכל שעה. she-Yisrael omrim shirah bechol sha'ah. We can say it at
any time we can sing to God and we דאווען daven three
times a day. מלאכי השרת אין אומרים שירה אלא פעם אחת ביום
malachei hashareis ein omrim shirah ela pa'am achas beyom only one time
during the day. And again with this theme of a very rare
opportunity. ואמרי לה פעם אחת בשבת V'amrei lah pa'am achas beshabas or
once every week. ואמרי לה פעם אחת בחודש V'amrei lah pa'am achas
bechodesh once a month. ואמרי לה פעם אחת בשנה V'amrei lah pa'am
achas beshanah once a year. ואמרי לה פעם אחת בשבוע V'amrei lah
pa'am achas beshavua once every seven years. ואמרי לה פעם אחת ביובל
V'amrei lah pa'am achas beyovel only once every fifty years. Now, it's
again not clear to me it means that no angel only all
the angels meaning no angel sing to God except once every fifty
years? It doesn't mean any particular angel only gets an opportunity once
every fifty years, seven years or fifty years which again fits better
with that
when it says they only do it every once a week or
once every year once every seven years. Does it mean that for
the intervening 6.9 years no angels are singing to God? Or does
it mean no angel all angels only do it? Or does it
mean any individual angel only gets an opportunity once every seven years?
But every day angels are praising God.
So that's the question.
Not the גמרא's question, it's my question.
No no, and the גמרא's question. No no no that's no, the
גמרא's question is no no no we're going to that's not the
גמרא's question. We'll get to the גמרא's question. Anyway I think the
latter makes more sense, it fits with the theme, "finally it's my
turn". It's hard to imagine that the גמרא even in praising the
way Israel is better than the angels would suggest that the angels
aren't singing to God regularly. But they say no we can do
it any day, the angels, any individual angel only gets a turn
at a very rare opportunity, which fits with the theme. So what
was the problem? Here's the problem. ואמרי לה פעם אחת בעולם V'amrei
lah pa'am achas be'olam some say only once in you know for
eternity. So it certainly seems like the point is any individual angel
only gets an opportunity maybe once in its lifetime and that fits
with this theme that you know the angel's saying "I have to
go now, it's finally my
chance". וישראל מזכירין את השם V'Yisrael mazkirin es Hashem not only does
Israel get to say it regularly, but they mention God's name אחר
שתי תיבות achar shtei teivos after saying two words, שנאמר שמע ישראל
ה׳ אלהינו ה׳ אחד shenemar Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu Hashem Echad which
is interesting that that's in the context of שירה, shirah, you wouldn't
necessarily call that שירה. shirah. ומלאכי השרת אין מזכירין את השם אלא
אחר ג׳ תיבות. U'malachei hashareis ein mazkirin es Hashem ela achar gimel
teivos. They have to wait till they say three words. כתיב קדוש
קדוש קדוש ה׳ צבאות. ksiv Kadosh Kadosh Kadosh Hashem Tzevaos. ואין מלאכי
השרת אומרים שירה למעלה V'ein malachei hashareis omrim shirah lemalah
not only that they don't sing to God above עד שיאמרו ישראל
שירה למטה. ad she-yomru Yisrael shirah lematah. So we sing to God
from below, שנאמר Shene'emar ברון יחד כוכבי בקר B'ron yachad kochvei voker
with the rejoicing together the stars of the morning which is understood
to be the Jewish people, והדר V'hadar and then it says ויריעו
כל בני אלהים V'yariu kol bnei elohim then all of the sons
of God meaning the angels will trumpet forth. Anyway what is the
question? The question is it says that they say three words and
then they say God's name, קדוש קדוש קדוש. Kadosh kadosh kadosh. And
we said that the third group of angels said קדוש ה' צבאות.
Kadosh Hashem Tzeva'ot. So they say God's name after one word, right?
Because we broke it up that the third group. So what's the
answer? אלא here's the answer, אחת אומרת קדוש Achas omeres kadosh one
first group says holy, ואחת אומרת קדוש קדוש V'achas omeres kadosh kadosh
holy holy, ואחת אומרת קדוש קדוש קדוש
ה' צבאות. V'achas omeres kadosh kadosh kadosh Hashem Tzeva'ot.
The third group has the first three as all the קדושים Kadoshes
and then they get to say God's name.
So they have to say it after three words, we say God's
name after two words.
All right. חזק. Chazak.
חזק חזק ונתחזק. Chazak chazak v'nischazek.